So I was trained to become a gymnast
تدربت لكي أصبح لاعبة جمباز
for two years in Hunan, China in the 1970s.
لمدة سنتين في هونان بالصين في السبعينات
When I was in the first grade, the government
عنما كنت في الصف الاول ، كانت الحكومة
wanted to transfer me to a school for athletes,
ترغب في تحويلي الى مدرسة للرياضيين ،
all expenses paid.
مع دفع كامل المصاريف
But my tiger mother said, "No."
لكن امي الشديدة رفضت ذلك وقالت " لا ".
My parents wanted me to become
والداي أرادا بأن أصبح
an engineer like them.
مهندسا مثلهما.
After surviving the Cultural Revolution,
بعد نجاتي من الثورة الثقافية ،
they firmly believed there's only one sure way to happiness:
اعتقدا وبشده أنه يوجد طريق واحد للسعاده :
a safe and well-paid job.
وظيفة امنة براتب جيد.
It is not important if I like the job or not.
ليس من المهم إذا كنت أرغب في العمل أم لا.
But my dream was to become a Chinese opera singer.
ولكن كان حلمي بأن أصبح مطربة أوبرا صينية
That is me playing my imaginary piano.
تلك هي أنا أعزف البيانو الوهمي.
An opera singer must start training young
مغني الأوبرا يجب أن يبدأ بالتدريب منذ الصغر
to learn acrobatics,
لكي يتعلم الحركات البهلوانية ،
so I tried everything I could to go to opera school.
لذا حاولت وبكل وسعي للذهاب الى مدرسة للأوبرا.
I even wrote to the school principal
حتى أنني كتبت الى مدير المدرسة
and the host of a radio show.
ومضيف برنامج إذاعي.
But no adults liked the idea.
ولكن لم يحب البالغين الفكرة.
No adults believed I was serious.
لم يعتقد أحد من البالغين بأني جاده
Only my friends supported me, but they were kids,
وحدهم هم أصدقائي الذين دعموني ، ولكنهم كانوا مجرد أطفال
just as powerless as I was.
فقط عاجزون مثلي
So at age 15, I knew I was too old to be trained.
لذلك في سن 15 سنة ، كنت أعرف بأنني أكبر من أتدرب
My dream would never come true.
حلمي لن يتحقق أبدا
I was afraid that for the rest of my life
كنت أخشى ولبقية حياتي
some second-class happiness
من بعض السعادة من الدرجة الثانية
would be the best I could hope for.
والتي ستكون بمثابة أفضل ما أمل به .
But that's so unfair.
ولكن هذا غير عادل.
So I was determined to find another calling.
لذا عزمت على إيجاد طريقة أخرى
Nobody around to teach me? Fine.
لا أحد حولي ليعلمني ؟ حسنا
I turned to books.
توجهت الى الكتب.
I satisfied my hunger for parental advice
أشبعت جوعي للنصائح الابوية
from this book by a family of writers and musicians.["Correspondence in the Family of Fou Lei"]
من هذا الكتاب المؤلف من قبل عائلة من الكتاب والموسيقيين [مراسلات عائلة فاو لي ]
I found my role model of an independent woman
لقد وجدت نموذجا يحتذى به من امرأة مستقلة
when Confucian tradition requires obedience.["Jane Eyre"]
عندما تتطلب التقاليد الكونفوشيوسية الطاعة [جين اير]
And I learned to be efficient from this book.["Cheaper by the Dozen"]
وتعلمت بأن أكون فعالا من هذا الكتاب [أرخص بالدرزن]
And I was inspired to study abroad after reading these.
قراءة هذه الكتب ألهمتني للدراسة في الخارج
["Complete Works of Sanmao" (aka Echo Chan)] ["Lessons From History" by Nan Huaijin]
["الأعمال الكاملة لسانماو" تأليف (أكا أيتشو شان)]["دروس من التأريخ" تأليف (نان هوايجين)]
I came to the U.S. in 1995,
جئت إلى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية في عام 1995
so which books did I read here first?
ما هي الكتب التي قرأتها هنا أولا ؟
Books banned in China, of course.
طبعا الكتب الممنوعة في الصين !
"The Good Earth" is about Chinese peasant life.
" الأرض الطيبة" كتاب عن حياة الفلاح الصيني
That's just not convenient for propaganda. Got it.
لم يكن قط مناسبا للدعاية .
The Bible is interesting, but strange.
الانجيل كتاب ممتع ما ولكن من الصعب فهمه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's a topic for a different day.
وهو موضوع ليوم آخر
But the fifth commandment gave me an epiphany:
ولكن الوصية الخامسة أعطتني نوع من الوحي :
"You shall honor your father and mother."
"عليك أن تحترم أباك وأمك"
"Honor," I said. "That's so different,
قلت "احترام". " هذا يختلف كثيرا،
and better, than obey."
وهو أفضل من الانصياع."
So it becomes my tool to climb out
لذا أصبحت أداتي للخروج
of this Confucian guilt trap
من مصيدة الذنب الكونفوشيوسي
and to restart my relationship with my parents.
وأيضا لاستئناف علاقتي مع والدي
Encountering a new culture also started my habit
مواجهة ثقافة جديدة جعلني أبدأ هوايتي
of comparative reading.
وهي قراءة المقارنة
It offers many insights.
التي توفر العديد من الأفكار
For example, I found this map out of place at first
على سبيل المثال ، وجدت هذه الخريطة في غير محلها
because this is what Chinese students grew up with.
لأنها هي التي اعتاد عليها الطلاب الصينيون
It had never occurred to me,
ولكن هذا لم يحدث معي ،
China doesn't have to be at the center of the world.
الصين ليس عليها أن تكون مركز العالم.
A map actually carries somebody's view.
في الواقع الخريطة تحمل رأي شخص ما.
Comparative reading actually is nothing new.
في الواقع قراءة المقارنة ليست بالجديدة
It's a standard practice in the academic world.
بل هي ممارسه في الحقل الاكاديمي .
There are even research fields
بل ان هناك مجالات للبحث
such as comparative religion and comparative literature.
فهناك المقارنة بين الأديان و المقارنة بين المؤلفات
Compare and contrast gives scholars
المقارنة والتباين يعطي الباحثين
a more complete understanding of a topic.
فهما أكثر للموضوع
So I thought, well, if comparative reading
لذلك فكرت، حسنا ، إذا كانت القراءة مقارنه
works for research, why not do it in daily life too?
فعالة في الأبحاث ، لماذا لا نفعل ذلك في الحياة اليومية أيضا؟
So I started reading books in pairs.
لذلك بدأت بقراءة الكتب بشكل ثنائي
So they can be about people --
حيث أنها يمكن أن تكون حول أشخاص
["Benjamin Franklin" by Walter Isaacson]["John Adams" by David McCullough] --
["بنيامين فرانكلين" تأليف والتر أسحاقسن]["جون ادمز" تأليف ديفيد مكولوف]
who are involved in the same event,
الذين يشتركون في نفس الحدث،
or friends with shared experiences.
أو الأصدقاء ذوي الخبرات المشتركة
["Personal History" by Katharine Graham]["The Snowball: Warren Buffett and the Business of Life," by Alice Schroeder]
[" التأريخ الشخصي " تأليف كاثرين جراهام ]["كرة الثلج" تأليف وارين بوفيت]و[" الحياة التجارية " تأليف أليس شرويدر ]
I also compare the same stories in different genres -- (Laughter)
أنا أيضا أقارن نفس القصص في أنواع مختلفة من الأدب (ضحك)
[Holy Bible: King James Version]["Lamb" by Chrisopher Moore] --
[الأنجيل المقدس : الملك جيمس فيرشن] ["الخروف" تأليف كريستوفر مور]
or similar stories from different cultures,
أو قصص مشابهة من مختلف الثقافات
as Joseph Campbell did in his wonderful book.["The Power of Myth" by Joseph Campbell]
مثل ما فعل جوزيف كامبل في كتابه الرائع ["قوة الأسطورة" ]
For example, both the Christ and the Buddha
على سبيل المثال، كلا من السيد المسيح وبوذا
went through three temptations.
مروا بثلاثة إغراءات
For the Christ, the temptations
للسيد المسيح للمسيح، الاغراءات
are economic, political and spiritual.
هي مغريات اقتصادية وسياسية وروحية
For the Buddha, they are all psychological:
بالنسبة لبوذا فهي جميعها نفسية :
lust, fear and social duty -- interesting.
الشهوة ، الخوف والعمل الاجتماعي ---- مثير للاهتمام
So if you know a foreign language, it's also fun
إذا كنت تعرف لغة أجنبية، فمن الممتع
to read your favorite books in two languages.
أن تقرأ كتبك المفضلة بلغتين
["The Way of Chuang Tzu" Thomas Merton]["Tao: The Watercourse Way" Alan Watts]
["طريق تشوانج تزو" تأليف توماس ميرتون]["تاو: طريق المجرى المائي" تأليف ألان واتس]
Instead of lost in translation, I found there is much to gain.
بدلا من الضياع في فهم الترجمة، وجدت هناك الكثير لأكسبه.
For example, it's through translation that I realized
على سبيل المثال، من خلال الترجمة أدركت أن
"happiness" in Chinese literally means "fast joy." Huh!
"السعادة" باللغة الصينية تعني حرفيا "الفرح بسرعة." هه
"Bride" in Chinese literally means "new mother." Uh-oh.
"العروس" باللغة الصينية تعني حرفيا "الأم الجديدة." أهووه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Books have given me a magic portal to connect with people
الكتب اعطتني بوابة سحرية للتواصل مع الناس
of the past and the present.
من الماضي والحاضر.
I know I shall never feel lonely or powerless again.
أعرف أنه يجب عليّ أن لا اشعر بالوحدة أو العجز مرة أخرى.
Having a dream shattered really is nothing
وجود حلم محطم حقا لا شيء
compared to what many others have suffered.
مقارنة بما يعانيه الكثيرون
I have come to believe that coming true
وصلت الى حقيقة مفادها أن تحقيق الحلم
is not the only purpose of a dream.
ليست الغاية الوحيدة للحلم
Its most important purpose is to get us in touch
الهدف الأهم هو جعلنا نتواصل
with where dreams come from,
مع مصدرهذه الأحلام ،
where passion comes from, where happiness comes from.
من حيث يأتي الشغف ، من حيث تأتي السعاده
Even a shattered dream can do that for you.
حتى الحلم المحطم يمكن أن يفعل ذلك لك.
So because of books, I'm here today,
لذا وبسبب الكتب، أنا هنا اليوم،
happy, living again with a purpose and a clarity,
سعيدة، اعيش مرة أخرى مع هدف ووضوح،
most of the time.
في اغلب الأوقات.
So may books be always with you.
لذا فلتكن الكتب دائما معكم
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)